<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://wearehalo.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://wearehalo.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2019-09-19T09:40:15+01:00</updated><id>https://wearehalo.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">❚ ♥ ❚</title><subtitle>Creative &amp; strategic partners to ambitious, purposeful brands. We partner with ambitious brands. Household names, energetic challengers, focused start-ups. Shaping &amp; connecting brands with their audiences. Creating emotional momentum.</subtitle></feed>
=======
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-05T16:35:55+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">❚ ♥ ❚</title><subtitle>Creative &amp; strategic partners to ambitious, purposeful brands. We partner with ambitious brands. Household names, energetic challengers, focused start-ups. Shaping &amp; connecting brands with their audiences. Creating emotional momentum.</subtitle></feed>
>>>>>>> Base blog structure
=======
=======
>>>>>>> Reprocessed files
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-05T16:36:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">❚ ♥ ❚</title><subtitle>Creative &amp; strategic partners to ambitious, purposeful brands. We partner with ambitious brands. Household names, energetic challengers, focused start-ups. Shaping &amp; connecting brands with their audiences. Creating emotional momentum.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Battle for Brand Purpose</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Battle for Brand Purpose" /><published>2019-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-battle-for-brand-purpose&quot;&gt;The Battle for Brand Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
=======
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-05T09:48:57+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">❚ ♥ ❚</title><subtitle>Creative &amp; strategic partners to ambitious, purposeful brands. We partner with ambitious brands. Household names, energetic challengers, focused start-ups. Shaping &amp; connecting brands with their audiences. Creating emotional momentum.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Battle for Brand Purpose</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Battle for Brand Purpose" /><published>2019-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-battle-for-brand-purpose&quot;&gt;The Battle for Brand Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;
>>>>>>> Reprocessed files
&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-to-get-back-to-reality&quot;&gt;Time to get back to reality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holly Tucker MBE, founder of Not On The High Street recently delivered some ‘sage’ advice
for brands at her keynote at MAD/Picnic. The resulting soundbites have snaked like demonic
whispering tendrils through social media, finding sycophantic agreement on LinkedIn and
confused disbelief in #strategytwitter. For those that missed it, here’s a few choice quotes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(Consumers) want to know everything about brands – engage with them, converse with
them, eat with them, listen with them, visit them and know what the brand stands for. They
want to get to know their circle and join a community of like-minded customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Customers buy experiences, not products. People want to share with their friends what they
did, not what they got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She went on to make grand statements about brands needing to establish a “mission for the
greater good” and “the brands of the future – the businesses that we’ll care about and
consume from – will be the ones with purpose.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a problem with this. I mean, on the surface, who am I to question Holly? She has a
wildly successful ecommerce business and a side hustle &lt;em&gt;shudder&lt;/em&gt; consultancy for
emerging brands. So she knows her stuff right? Well, yes, it would appear so, but when it
comes to ‘brand purpose’ – as far as I’m concerned, she’s utterly deluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brand-purpose-is-not-csr&quot;&gt;Brand purpose is not CSR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure when brand purpose became a spiritual black hole, with meaningless platitudes
orbiting the event horizon, beaconing marketeers towards its gaping maw with siren calls
promising Millennial and GenZ engagement. But here we are, desperately searching for a
greater meaning in an industry that needs to dial down the bullshit and start having honest
conversations with itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the easy stuff. Consumers do not want brands to eat with them, listen with
them or visit them. They don’t want a stalker with a logo ruining their dinner, sharing it’s
playlists and appearing at the front door like a middle aged Jehovah’s Witness in skinny
jeans. And I’m pretty sure when people shop at Not On The High Street, they’re looking for
an apron with ‘gin o’clock’ written on it rather than the ‘experience’ Holly would lead us to
believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s ok. Because brands don’t always need to be more than a vehicle for commerce.
And if they try to be, commerce will nearly always get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t expect Starbucks to actually ‘nurture communities one cup at a time’, they could do
that by paying tax, but that would hurt their profits. Don’t expect Gillette to really care
about breaking down the patriarchy, because when women pay more for their razors than
men it makes the bottom line look far more silkily attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying that businesses shouldn’t be responsible for their societal and environmental
impact, but that goes beyond brand. Because most people don’t really give a toss about a
brand’s supposed good intentions or liberal ethics. They care about value and availability.
They care about 24hr delivery. If they cared about social equality they wouldn’t shop at
Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses must strive to deliver great products and customer service and do so in a socially
and environmentally conscious way. We, the consumer should expect that the brands we
consume are doing the right thing. But when a brand uses liberal ethics and ideals as a
marketing strategy, pushing a moral code in order to push product, it’s as thin and fragile as
a skin graft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;purpose-used-to-mean-something&quot;&gt;Purpose used to mean something&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose for me, has always been about a brand’s role in people’s lives. Based on product
truths, values upheld by behaviour, the shaping and interpretation of that brand by mutual
agreement with the customer. Purpose is not about pursuing audience approval by aligning
with a perceived morality that fits the zeitgeist. Purpose was never about changing the
world. It was about changing the customer’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that was big enough. Meaningful enough.
Truthful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want trainers that smell of park runs and 10Ks, not sweat shops and child labour.
I want a flat white that comes with a double shot of espresso and paid corporation tax.
I don’t need my kitchen surface cleaner to come with storytelling.
I don’t need to join a community of other ‘like-minded’ people who like olives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t need business ‘influencers’ selling the industry short, standing tall on a
conference podium in front of a PowerPoint deck with low meaning but high impact based
on nothing more than the speakers elevated status and financial success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Brand Purpose used to be important and valuable.
Stop fucking it up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Ellis</name></author><summary type="html">The Battle for Brand Purpose Time to get back to reality</summary></entry></feed>
>>>>>>> Updated post dates and URLs, as well as added some additional quality of life styling for the blog post content
