<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2019-10-16T15:20:31+01:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//feed.xml</id><title type="html">❚ ♥ ❚</title><subtitle>Creative &amp; strategic partners to ambitious, purposeful brands. We partner with ambitious brands. Household names, energetic challengers, focused start-ups. Shaping &amp; connecting brands with their audiences. Creating emotional momentum.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Battle for Brand Purpose</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Battle for Brand Purpose"/><published>2019-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/07/16/the-battle-for-brand-purpose/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-to-get-back-to-reality&quot;&gt;Time to get back to reality&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Holly Tucker MBE, founder of Not On The High Street recently delivered some ‘sage’ advice for brands at her keynote at MAD/Picnic. The resulting soundbites have snaked like demonic whispering tendrils through social media, finding sycophantic agreement on LinkedIn and confused disbelief in #strategytwitter. For those that missed it, here’s a few choice quotes:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;(Consumers) want to know everything about brands – engage with them, converse with them, eat with them, listen with them, visit them and know what the brand stands for. They want to get to know their circle and join a community of like-minded customers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Customers buy experiences, not products. People want to share with their friends what they did, not what they got.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;She went on to make grand statements about brands needing to establish a “mission for the greater good” and “the brands of the future – the businesses that we’ll care about and consume from – will be the ones with purpose.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I have a problem with this. I mean, on the surface, who am I to question Holly? She has a wildly successful ecommerce business and a side hustle &lt;em&gt;shudder&lt;/em&gt; consultancy for emerging brands. So she knows her stuff right? Well, yes, it would appear so, but when it comes to ‘brand purpose’ – as far as I’m concerned, she’s utterly deluded.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;brand-purpose-is-not-csr&quot;&gt;Brand purpose is not CSR&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m not sure when brand purpose became a spiritual black hole, with meaningless platitudes orbiting the event horizon, beaconing marketeers towards its gaping maw with siren calls promising Millennial and GenZ engagement. But here we are, desperately searching for a greater meaning in an industry that needs to dial down the bullshit and start having honest conversations with itself.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the easy stuff. Consumers do not want brands to eat with them, listen with them or visit them. They don’t want a stalker with a logo ruining their dinner, sharing it’s playlists and appearing at the front door like a middle aged Jehovah’s Witness in skinny jeans. And I’m pretty sure when people shop at Not On The High Street, they’re looking for an apron with ‘gin o’clock’ written on it rather than the ‘experience’ Holly would lead us to believe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And that’s ok. Because brands don’t always need to be more than a vehicle for commerce. And if they try to be, commerce will nearly always get in the way.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Don’t expect Starbucks to actually ‘nurture communities one cup at a time’, they could do that by paying tax, but that would hurt their profits. Don’t expect Gillette to really care about breaking down the patriarchy, because when women pay more for their razors than men it makes the bottom line look far more silkily attractive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m not saying that businesses shouldn’t be responsible for their societal and environmental impact, but that goes beyond brand. Because most people don’t really give a toss about a brand’s supposed good intentions or liberal ethics. They care about value and availability. They care about 24hr delivery. If they cared about social equality they wouldn’t shop at Amazon.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Businesses must strive to deliver great products and customer service and do so in a socially and environmentally conscious way. We, the consumer should expect that the brands we consume are doing the right thing. But when a brand uses liberal ethics and ideals as a marketing strategy, pushing a moral code in order to push product, it’s as thin and fragile as a skin graft.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;purpose-used-to-mean-something&quot;&gt;Purpose used to mean something&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Purpose for me, has always been about a brand’s role in people’s lives. Based on product truths, values upheld by behaviour, the shaping and interpretation of that brand by mutual agreement with the customer. Purpose is not about pursuing audience approval by aligning with a perceived morality that fits the zeitgeist. Purpose was never about changing the world. It was about changing the customer’s world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And that was big enough. Meaningful enough. Truthful.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I want trainers that smell of park runs and 10Ks, not sweat shops and child labour. I want a flat white that comes with a double shot of espresso and paid corporation tax. I don’t need my kitchen surface cleaner to come with storytelling. I don’t need to join a community of other ‘like-minded’ people who like olives.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I don’t need business ‘influencers’ selling the industry short, standing tall on a conference podium in front of a PowerPoint deck with low meaning but high impact based on nothing more than the speakers elevated status and financial success.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Because Brand Purpose used to be important and valuable. Stop fucking it up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nick Ellis</name></author><summary type="html">Time to get back to reality</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Points of Parity Benefit Brands</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/04/02/how-points-of-parity-benefit-brands/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Points of Parity Benefit Brands"/><published>2019-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/04/02/how-points-of-parity-benefit-brands</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/04/02/how-points-of-parity-benefit-brands/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-uk-in-recent-years-there-has-been-an-emergence-of-a-number-of-challenger-bank-brands&quot;&gt;In the UK in recent years there has been an emergence of a number of challenger bank brands.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the UK in recent years there has been an emergence of a number of challenger bank brands. Monzo, Dozens, and Starling Bank, among many others, may well be trying to disrupt the banking sector, but they’ve recently faced the accusation of appearing all too similar. Looking at their advertisements in isolation, yes they don’t appear all that differentiated.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, it might be helpful to consider the wider context these banks are working in. At this stage of the life of their brand are they really fighting each other, or are they fighting the huge banking giants for market share and customers. Considering the whole context of their market and competitor landscape, surely it’s these huge banking brands they’re looking to differentiate from.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alongside the desire to stand apart and appear different from the huge banks, might we suggest that there is also a value to them being seen as a part of this group of disruptor banking brands.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the early years, there is a value to these banks in the points-of-parity they have with other banks that they hope the audience associate them with. These banking brands are creating an identity, not only for themselves, but for the wider idea of doing your banking differently.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The approach of brands within a category having common visual cues is nothing new. Just think about washing detergents, and how many visual similarities they have, from graphic devices to typographic treatments. Another example might be craft beer brewers who, particularly in the early years of the growing movement, created brands and identities that stood them apart from the large breweries and beers, rather than from each other within the craft beer category.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m sure there are more examples, and there are always outliers within categories for whom this won’t be true, but the point remains that there are many instances where having common visual cues across brands in a certain category can act as a kind of shorthand to help the audience identify those brands as a part of a group.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Seth Godin recently touched on something similar in his post ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://seths.blog/2019/04/next-to-the-competition-2/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Next To The Competition&lt;/a&gt;’, in which he wrote:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Trade show booths work when they’re in close proximity to the other options a buyer has. Building your trade show booth across town might insulate you from the other choices, but it does little to help establish where you belong and whether or not you’re a smart choice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;And if I was a wedding photographer, I’d organize a dozen other photographers in town and do a joint brochure and marketing effort. Serving brides in a way that establishes status and increases their confidence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;being-identified-as-a-part-of-a-group-can-be-beneficial&quot;&gt;Being identified as a part of a group can be beneficial.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now of course, a brand should have its own identity – but let’s also remember that, particularly when the competition you’re actually trying to win customers from is so much larger and with a much larger available budget, there is a value in being identified as one of a group – in this case disruptor banking brands. By looking similar in their advertising these brands are (intentionally or not) working as a group, sending similar messages to their audience in an attempt to shape an awareness and perception of this type of disruptor banking brand in the minds of their potential customers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is a value in creating points-of-difference for your brand, but there can also be value in the points-of-parity with alike brands, particularly when you would benefit from a strength in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Bailey</name></author><summary type="html">In the UK in recent years there has been an emergence of a number of challenger bank brands.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Power of Simple Brand Experiences</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/01/17/the-power-of-simple-brand-experiences/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Power of Simple Brand Experiences"/><published>2019-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/01/17/the-power-of-simple-brand-experiences</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2019/01/17/the-power-of-simple-brand-experiences/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-have-a-new-favorite-toy-store-brand&quot;&gt;I have a new favorite toy store brand.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;I don’t know what their logo looks like. I have no idea how simple their digital user journeys are. I know nothing of their brand purpose, or even if they have one. What I do know, is that one experience I had with them this week has left a hugely positive and abiding memory… and it was all about the bubbles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I have a 21month old son. It’s a fantastic age and it’s fascinating and beautiful to see him play happily. On a recent visit to Bath (in the UK) we popped in to a small toy store in the center of the city. The store was full of fantastic toys, but one display of toys in particular took our son’s attention.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I don’t know what it is about backhoes, dump trucks, and cranes, but our son is fascinated – and the display of a set of glorious, wooden construction vehicles was all he needed to keep him entertained. Now, while one of us was looking around the store this was great, and a welcome distraction that kept him busy. However, the big issue was when it was time to leave the store. Have you tried persuading a 21 month old boy, obsessed with construction vehicles, to walk away from a large set of construction vehicles? Not an easy task.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Up to this point, our experience of the store had been fine. Nice toys, attentive staff, and a pleasant store. All good so far… but not memorable, nor particularly exceptional. However, this all changed when it was time for us to leave.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As I was using persuasion technique number eighteen to encourage leaving the construction set behind, a staff member approached my son and myself.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;‘Have you seen the bubbles outside?’ she said to my son.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, the one thing more appealing than construction vehicles to this 21 month old is bubbles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He looked up at her, wide-eyed. Bubbles?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At first I hadn’t realized what she was doing, but it quickly dawned on me that this was obviously not the first time there had been a child who was much more keen to stay than to leave.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This promise of bubbles had done the trick. The staff member led the way outside the store, and preceded to blow some bubbles – much to our son’s delight. Thirty seconds of bubbles washed away all memories of construction toys, and off we went on our day out as happy as we’d been when entering the store.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now, this might sound a little corny, but this small act made a huge impression on me. Had this staff member not intervened, my last experience of the store would likely have been a difficult one. I could even have still been there now trying to persuade him of the merits of leaving behind such great toys. As it was though, my last and abiding memory of the toy store was of one that clearly understands its target audience, and vitally the key situations they might find themselves in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Experiences have become vitally important to the shaping of a brand. In ‘The Experience Economy’, Pine &amp;amp; Gilmore state that experience is the “&lt;em&gt;fourth economic offering&lt;/em&gt;”. From commodity to goods, to service and then experience. A commodity or good has a finite usefulness and a service is a specific exchange, but an experience lives on in our memories forever. In fact, our memories are key to the experience economy. As Pine &amp;amp; Gilmore state “&lt;em&gt;the value of the experience lingers in the memory of any individual who was engaged by the event&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When working with clients, I often explain that a brand is shaped by creating and encouraging Associated Memorable Moments. These are moments that are memorable, hopefully for the right reasons, and that we associate with the brand. Whether this moment with the bubbles was a result of very smart and insightful staff training, or just one brilliant member of staff who really understood their customers, it left behind a memory which will help shape the brand of this toy store to me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Brand experience doesn’t have to be hugely expensive, or complicated, to be effective. To display an understanding of your audience, and a response which creates a positive experience for them, can be as simple as blowing bubbles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;(Note: If you’re ever in Bath, UK, why not pay a visit to the award-winning independent My Small World Toy Store. You might even get to see some bubbles.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Bailey</name></author><summary type="html">I have a new favorite toy store brand.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Brands and The Changing Art of Persuasion</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/09/04/brands-and-the-changing-art-of-persuasion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brands and The Changing Art of Persuasion"/><published>2018-09-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-09-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/09/04/brands-and-the-changing-art-of-persuasion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/09/04/brands-and-the-changing-art-of-persuasion/">&lt;p&gt;I recently attended a great morning session on strategy at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ycn.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;You Can Now (YCN)&lt;/a&gt; here in London. It included some fantastic insight from strategists who sit at different stages of their professional lives – James Lees (Sword &amp;amp; Stone) and Jim Carroll (ex-UK Chairman of BBH). Both made some great points, but the big takeaway from the talk for me was from Jim regarding ‘persuasion’, and that a part of our role as strategists remains to persuade.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;persuasion-is-not-the-most-fashionable-of-brand-p-words-right-now--that-honor-goes-to-purpose&quot;&gt;Persuasion is not the most fashionable of brand P-words right now – that honor goes to Purpose.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Purpose has become the phrase on every brand strategists lips, but unfortunately this is a phrase which I feel has become hijacked. Having a purpose for your brand is of course important, but how this is defined has become rather confused. For me, every brand should have a purpose or aspiration which they share with their audience. Whether this is a social purpose, such as minimizing plastic waste, or simply a shared aspiration, such as improving your fitness, this can encourage people to become interested and involved with a brand. (If you want to actually read some intelligent writing around brand purpose then try &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Q0GYZL&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Citizen Brands by Michael Willmott&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2oECwmQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beyond Branding by Nicholas Ind&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2wG1W8c&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cannibals with Forks by John Elkington&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But is defining a purpose for your brand simply another way to persuade people that they should be interested in your brand, or want to join your brand ‘tribe’? I believe there is a danger that we feel that persuasion is what those Mad Men advertising execs of the 60s/70s/80s/90s did, and now we want to have ‘conversations’ with our target audience on what the brand means to them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes a brand must be shaped around a meaning which is shared with people, and brand communications should now be two way conversations in some form (in that we must actively listen to what people are saying). But as strategists, and importantly the people leading a brand, it is our role to always seek to move the conversation on and constantly seek to shape the conversation that is being had.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So is a part of our role still as persuaders? I may be wrong here, but I feel that many of today’s marketers consider persuasion to be beneath them. Talking about things like brand purpose help us make our role sound more worthwhile, and make us feel better about ourselves, but is there anything wrong with seeking to persuade?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:6435406409462013952&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;I shared the topic of persuasion on LinkedIn recently and was challenged by Merlin Duff&lt;/a&gt; (strategy consultant at Venturethree) whether we seek to persuade or influence? Merlin’s delineation between the two was that ‘everything we do is about influence but not necessarily about persuasion (if by persuasion we mean persuading people to do/think/feel something).’ Although we agreed that there are semantics at play here, we did discuss the interesting difference between the two terms of persuasion and influence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Personally, I question whether some strategists, marketers, etc might feel a little unnerved by the thought that they are encouraging people to do/think/feel something. If we are being tasked by a brand owner (whether as an external or internal expert) to help them with a specific challenge for their brand, surely we have to accept that to seek to influence is not enough. We need to be increasing awareness and affiliation, but with the ultimate aim of encouraging desired actions – which fundamentally is persuading isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For those Mad Men ad execs mentioned previously, their tools of persuasion were the ‘megaphone’ media of advertising, in its various forms. I believe that the role of persuasion does remain, but the tools may now be different. In our networked world, persuasion doesn’t have to come directly from the ‘mouth’ of the organization. Harvard Business Review recently featured an article on the role of online peer-reviews in persuading people, finding that it is actually moderately positive reviews that are the most persuasive. We’ve also mentioned influence, and so can’t omit the ‘persuasive powers’ of those social media influencers who seem to be so popular with some marketers these days. The ethics of some social media influencers may be questionable, with the recent claims of some beauty influencers offering to give negative reviews of competitor brands for $75k, but the fact that they are simply another way by which to persuade should be beyond doubt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In rather apt timing, Tom Roach (Managing Partner BBH London) shared a tweet recently reminding me of the, admittedly very catchy, idea that it is now about ‘Making things people want’ rather than ‘Making people want things’. His point was that, although ‘Making things people want’ is important, we are in danger of forgetting how to ‘Make people want things’. I agree, although I don’t believe we can ‘make’ people want things, but surely it is incumbent on us to accept our role as persuaders. We obviously would like our clients or bosses to think that our work is encouraging desired actions, as if they didn’t then our jobs would surely be in question.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Of course, if we are persuading people to engage with or be interested in specific brands then I feel that we must believe that there genuinely is some value and benefit in the brand to people. As the excellent strategist Faris asked in a tweet when discussing this subject, is there ‘an ethical boundary to persuasion’?. I say that yes there is, but what is ethical to one person differs to what is ethical to another. What we are willing and prepared to seek to persuade people to do, or buy, or join, or believe, or share in, is a personal decision and should be guided by our own personal ethics.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;the-tools-of-persuasion-may-have-changed-but-the-art-of-persuasion-remains-an-essential-role-for-strategists&quot;&gt;The tools of persuasion may have changed, but the art of persuasion remains an essential role for strategists.&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Bailey</name></author><summary type="html">I recently attended a great morning session on strategy at the You Can Now (YCN) here in London. It included some fantastic insight from strategists who sit at different stages of their professional lives – James Lees (Sword &amp;amp; Stone) and Jim Carroll (ex-UK Chairman of BBH). Both made some great points, but the big takeaway from the talk for me was from Jim regarding ‘persuasion’, and that a part of our role as strategists remains to persuade.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Brand Change Triggers Emotional Reactions</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/05/02/why-brand-change-triggers-emotional-reactions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Brand Change Triggers Emotional Reactions"/><published>2018-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/05/02/why-brand-change-triggers-emotional-reactions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/05/02/why-brand-change-triggers-emotional-reactions/">&lt;p&gt;Brand is used to appeal to peoples’ emotions, by creating meaning that has a value to someone. So why is there any surprise if people react emotionally when organizations (or their brand agencies) make changes to a brand?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;meaning-and-self-identity&quot;&gt;Meaning and Self-Identity&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Brands are laden with symbolism and meaning, and a large part of that meaning is the idea of identity. Of course, there is the identity of the brand itself – what the brand represents and how it appears – but a brand can also go to make up a constituent part of a person’s self identity. In being an ‘insider’ of a brand an individual may become a part of a ‘tribe’ (a group of people who share ideals, values, aspirations, meaning, through the brand), and it is this sense of belonging to a tribe which goes to help form part of their self-identity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Zygmunt Bauman puts this much more succinctly in Celia Lury’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2rbodXM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Consumer Culture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;For the individual, joining a tribe means adopting a peculiar lifestyle; or, rather, the road to a coherent lifestyle leads through the adoption of tribally sanctioned structure of relevance complete with a kit of totemic symbols.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;If we consider a brand in terms of helping form a persons self-identity, then by changing elements of a brand that in part form the ‘totemic symbols’ it could be argued that we are also changing part of a person’s self-identity. So, as brand leaders, if we are changing a part of a persons self-identity we need to be prepared for the inevitable push back from them. Particularly if this change has been made without the consultation or permission of the individual.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some brands appeal much more to peoples emotions and surely there can be no brands more emotionally-resonant than those of sports clubs. By looking at peoples’ reactions to changes in sports club brands, we can see extreme examples of how people respond when a change is made to a brand, and as a consequence their self-identity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ultimate-emotional-brands--sports-clubs&quot;&gt;The Ultimate Emotional Brands – Sports Clubs&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sports clubs engender a loyalty that other organizations can only dream of. Once someone has set their heart on a club then (usually) they are committed for life, in good times and bad. Imagine that once someone has chosen a soft drink in their youth that becomes the only drink that will pass their lips…ever. This is great for the sports club, but what this level of commitment and loyalty creates is a sense of ‘ownership’ of the brand by its fans.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A sports club may like to think that they own their brand, but there are numerous examples of club owners falling foul when trying to do something the fans didn’t approve of, or didn’t fit their idea of the role the brand plays in the creation of their self-identity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here in the UK, football is a hugely popular sport, and it has seen some of the biggest reactions to changes in a brand. In 2010 Assem Allam bought a football club, Hull City, and decided that their name ‘City’ was too common. His ambition was for the club to become a globally recognizable brand, and so decided to change their name from City to something more unique and ownable. Allam attempted to rename the club Hull Tigers, but the fans protested vociferously. Even though the club nickname already actually is Tigers, the fans simply weren’t prepared to accept the name change. The FA [footballs governing body in the UK] rejected the name change request, twice, and so the club remains Hull City. Allam might own the football club, but he discovered that he doesn’t own the brand – although he hasn’t quite given up the wrestle of control of the brand just yet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Another example in football is that of Cardiff City, and their football uniform color and badge. Cardiff City has been known as the Bluebirds since 1908, but that didn’t stop their new owner Vincent Tan from changing their uniform from blue (which they had also worn since 1908) to red. He also changed their badge from featuring the bluebird to using a dragon. His plan was simple, in order to become a global brand Cardiff City needed to utilize existing references to Wales, i.e. a red dragon (it is on the Welsh flag after all). The strategy was to tie Cardiff City to Wales, and in so doing make the club a more appealing and identifiable brand globally. Maybe it did, but again the fans weren’t happy. Fan protests took place and in 2015 they changed back to being the Bluebirds, with the bird on their badge, and playing in blue. Again, the owner might own the club but he didn’t own the brand.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One final example is that of Bristol Rugby Football Club, a rugby union team based in the UK city of Bristol (unsurprisingly). They have recently been promoted to the top division of rugby, and to capitalize on this success have launched a new identity and most controversially a new name – Bristol Bears. Naming a sports team after an animal is nothing new, certainly not to US sports fans, but there isn’t a great deal of history of this in the UK – and there is certainly no history of bears in Bristol. The new name has caused uproar with fans, with accusations of the club ‘Americanization’ and of robbing the club and brand of its history. How this plays out we shall see in the near future, but for now a large percentage of the audience (74% in a recent poll) feel that the brand has changed to an identity which they don’t really want as a part of their self-identity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;be-prepared-for-a-reaction-its-actually-good-that-people-care&quot;&gt;Be Prepared For A Reaction. It’s Actually Good That People Care&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;We could go on and on listing examples, but the lesson is always the same. Should a brand have a existing emotional connection with its audience, then any changes made to this brand – and therefore by association an individual’s self-identity – must be handled with care. Whether changing a name, a logo, or a color, what is also being changed is a part of that individuals’ self-identity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Any business or organization wanting to make changes to a brand to which people have a strong emotional connection need to ensure that changes be discussed with, approved by or co-created with the people who really ‘own’ the brand – the audience. Developing a sense of mutual trust between the organization and the audience is central to having any changes be welcomed, embraced and succeeding.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Very few organizations’ brands have the emotional connection sports clubs do, but if as brand leaders we aspire for people to emotionally connect with a brand then we cannot be surprised or offended when people react emotionally to any changes. In fact, if people do react emotionally then it shows we are doing something right and they care about what the brand means to and says about them. If we are altering a part of a persons self-identity, then the very least we can do is consult them during the process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Bailey</name></author><summary type="html">Brand is used to appeal to peoples’ emotions, by creating meaning that has a value to someone. So why is there any surprise if people react emotionally when organizations (or their brand agencies) make changes to a brand?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Brand Utility Shields Facebook</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/03/26/how-brand-utility-shields-facebook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Brand Utility Shields Facebook"/><published>2018-03-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/03/26/how-brand-utility-shields-facebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/03/26/how-brand-utility-shields-facebook/">&lt;p&gt;Why do people remain loyal to a brand? There are a myriad of benefits that brand experts claim people want from a brand – collaboration, service, innovation, relationships, and the current favorite, purpose. Obviously there are many reasons people are loyal to a specific brand, but what about when a brand is simultaneously extremely successful and unpopular with the people using it? Why would people remain loyal to a brand they didn’t like?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Just in case you’ve been hiding under a rock for a few weeks I will fill you in – the Facebook brand has been taking a bit of a kicking recently. Without going in to detail (the plethora of issues are too confusing to be honest, but Cambridge Analytica and the misuse of 50 million sets of peoples’ information are pretty high on the list) it seems that Facebook haven’t been all that great at being a trustworthy brand.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;People have essentially been giving their data to Facebook for years, but the lack of care Facebook have taken with this data is now coming into sharp focus. The hashtag #deletefacebook has gained notable traction on social media, and the Bank of America has slashed the Facebook share price forecast citing this hashtag ‘movement’ as a reason. Although the hashtag, and the sentiment to leave, has been widely shared there is little evidence people are actually leaving in huge numbers. In a recent interview Mark Zuckerberg responded to a question on the #deletefacebook campaign by saying that they haven’t seen a meaningful number of people leave the platform.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;brand-utility--brand-armour&quot;&gt;Brand Utility = Brand Armour&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is the key point regarding Facebook. What can easily be forgotten in shaping brand is the simple factor of utility. What does the brand (and business) allow people to do, and what value does this represent to them?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Facebook has so embedded itself into modern society, that in deleting it people wouldn’t simply be leaving a brand, but would be losing friendships and communities. If society is formed by our shared space, then Facebook has managed to make itself integral to our digital society. In fact, the dictionary definition of society – the aggregate of people living together in a more or less ordered community – pretty much defines Facebook’s utility in the digital sphere.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some commentators have mentioned that other social platforms had their time in the sun but were eventually replaced (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_defunct_social_networking_websites&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MySpace, Friendster, Orkut&lt;/a&gt;) and that Facebook could go the way of these. I’m not convinced of this, and the reason is the utility of the brand. Facebook has placed itself at the center of an incalculable number of relationships, many of which would simply would not exist without it. The brand has little competition right now, and the sheer number of people on the platform means that it remains in a dominant position.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is this unique utility Facebook offers which seems to continue to outweigh any issues people might have with trust in the brand. The opinion of the Facebook brand must be at an all time low right now – many people don’t trust the content they are shown on it, or what Facebook will do with their own data. In fact, Facebook is the big tech company that people trust the least, with 80% of people in one survey saying they don’t trust Facebook with their data.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However little the Facebook brand is trusted right now, it is going to be very interesting to see how long the value of the utility of this platform remains greater than the lack of trust in the brand. Only when this equation reverses – when the requirement for trust outweighs the utility on offer – might we actually see people #deleteFacebook.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Bailey</name></author><summary type="html">Why do people remain loyal to a brand? There are a myriad of benefits that brand experts claim people want from a brand – collaboration, service, innovation, relationships, and the current favorite, purpose. Obviously there are many reasons people are loyal to a specific brand, but what about when a brand is simultaneously extremely successful and unpopular with the people using it? Why would people remain loyal to a brand they didn’t like?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Myth Of The More Socially Conscious Millennials</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/01/03/the-myth-of-the-more-socially-conscious-millennials/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Myth Of The More Socially Conscious Millennials"/><published>2018-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/01/03/the-myth-of-the-more-socially-conscious-millennials</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2018/01/03/the-myth-of-the-more-socially-conscious-millennials/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;73-of-millennials-are-willing-to-spend-more-on-a-product-if-it-comes-from-a-sustainable-brand-81-of-millennials-expect-their-favorite-companies-to-make-public-declarations-of-their-corporate-citizenship&quot;&gt;73% of millennials are willing to spend more on a product if it comes from a sustainable brand. 81% of millennials expect their favorite companies to make public declarations of their corporate citizenship.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;These statistics from Nielson’s 2015 Global Corporate Sustainability Report, and others like them, are informing a popular view that Millennials are demanding businesses and organizations be more socially conscious and responsible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, are we to assume from this that people born between 1982 and 2002 (the Millennials) are more socially conscious than previous generations? If so, why would this be the case? Maybe we should take a step back from the popular view, and consider whether this is actually what the statistics are telling us, or is there something else happening here?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I challenge whether the Millennial generation are actually more driven by social causes at all, and put forward an alternative hypothesis. I have no specific evidence as such, but this is food for thought which challenges the current consensus and reading of the statistics.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The idea that ‘Millennials’ are more socially conscious than any generation before is a myth, and simply one interpretation of the evidence.  &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What I suggest has happened is that the self-identity of people within this generation (‘Millennials’) has become so enmeshed with their associations and relationships with consumer brands that they see brands as their best route to affecting social change.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The role of the person as consumer, rather than citizen, has been covered in great depth by academics such as Celia Lury in Consumer Culture. Being born in 1982 at the earliest, Millennials have only ever lived in a time when consumer culture was a pervasive force. Increasingly, the consumer is being considered as an ‘active’ consumer who can ‘add-value’. This value can be either financial or in the form of intrinsic or extrinsic benefits seen by the company or consumer, from ’McDonaldization’ where consumers provide immaterial labor (Zwick, Bonsu and Darmody, 2008) to ‘co-creation’ and ‘prosumption’ where the consumer is the ‘producer’ of unique value (Ritzer and Jurgenson, 2010).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As a person’s role as an active consumer becomes more pervasive, the place brands have in shaping a person’s identity becomes more central. However, when previous generations were at the ages Millennials are now, the role that consumer brands played in their lives were different. A person’s role as citizen or civic activist was more distinct from that of their role as consumer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Think of the social movements of the 50s, 60s, 70s – these were times when there were very active voices for social consciousness and activism, but simply not through the prism of brands and the role as consumer. The pervasiveness of the role as consumer has blurred the distinction between citizen and consumer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Celia Lury put it this way, ‘Consumer choice’ is still the means by which our society thinks about individual agency and autonomy and makes judgements (good or bad) about personal identity. The significance of consumer culture is thus to be found in the fact that the individual is no longer judged by him or herself or by society in terms of how well they carry out their duty or responsibility in relation to some wider collective or external morality (‘the family’, ‘the community’, ‘the greater good of all’ or ‘God’s will’), but in terms of how well they exercise their capacity to make a (consumer) choice.’&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Consumer brands have so co-opted the social and cultural landscapes, that young people see their role as consumer as that in which they have the most impact.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The self-identity of ‘Millennials’ has become so enmeshed with consumer brands, it seems their best way to encourage social change.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Why is this distinction important? My argument isn’t that Millennials aren’t being more demanding of businesses and organizations to be more socially conscious and responsible, but that Millennials are no more socially conscious than previous generations and it is simply that they see their role as consumer as their best bet to affect social change.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As people working with brand, when we are considering how we understand and communicate to our audience it is vital to try to understand what the motivations are, and the reasons behind differences between peoples’ decision making. It is important to make our decisions based on quantitive metrics, but we mustn’t forget the need to look behind the numbers so that we fully understand context.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To best work with and shape brand we need to keep asking questions, and not simply accept the consensus opinion. Always interrogate the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Bailey</name></author><summary type="html">73% of millennials are willing to spend more on a product if it comes from a sustainable brand. 81% of millennials expect their favorite companies to make public declarations of their corporate citizenship.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Boaty McBoatface – A lesson in co-creation</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2016/05/26/boaty-mcboatface-lesson-co-creation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boaty McBoatface – A lesson in co-creation"/><published>2016-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2016/05/26/boaty-mcboatface-lesson-co-creation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2016/05/26/boaty-mcboatface-lesson-co-creation/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;earlier-this-year-the-natural-environment-research-council-launched-a-poll-to-name-their-royal-research-ship-using-the-hashtag-nameourship-a-royal-research-ship-rrs-conducts-scientific-research-for-her-majestys-government-no-less-so-this-is-respectable-important-stuff&quot;&gt;Earlier this year the Natural Environment Research Council launched a poll to name their Royal Research Ship, using the hashtag #NameOurShip. A Royal Research Ship (RRS) conducts scientific research for Her Majesty’s Government no less, so this is respectable, important stuff.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;when-the-voting-had-ended-the-clear-winning-name-was-rrs-boaty-mcboatface&quot;&gt;When the voting had ended, the clear winning name was RRS Boaty McBoatface.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;In an increasingly digital-led age there is a clamour to engage and involve people in brands. However, there are smart ways of involving people and not so smart ways – and #BoatyMcBoatface is a great example of being not so smart.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Co-creation is become an increasingly used buzz phrase, but there is considerable misunderstanding of what it means to co-create a brand. There is some very intelligent and insightful literature on co-creation and the sociological and psychological theories behind it, but I doubt many marketers have read any Prahalad or Ramaswamy. I think it is time they did.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Importantly, co-creation is about the business and people jointly creating ‘value’. Shared value around a brand which has been co-created can be an extremely effective way of building a relationship between business and people. The value is often in an improved or more bespoke experience of the brand.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Where the misuse of co-creation often occurs is in the assumption that people will see the same value in doing something as you do. The Boaty McBoatface example is a good one, but it is far from a one-off. Giving the public the ability to name a ship, anything they want at all, had ‘value’ to them. The problem was the value in being able to choose a name that would reflect the gravitas of the ship and project, was outweighed by the value people saw in subverting the obvious desired outcome. People knew that those instigating the naming process would like a name reflective of the prestige of the ship, which is exactly why the value to people of choosing a name that was the opposite of this was so strong. Once a name was suggested that had the right amount of wit and ‘stickiness’, there was only ever going to be one winner. Boaty McBoatface it was.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it wasn’t. In a bit of a pr management exercise, the small print of the competition was outlined which said that the most popular name didn’t HAVE to be used. And so the ship is to be named the RRS Sir David Attenborough, which is much more in line with the mission of the vessel. However, Boaty McBoatface is still to be used as the name of one of the remotely operated vehicles. Now this was actually pretty smart handling for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;everyone loves Sir David Attenborough, and so people are unlikely to complain too much about the ship being named after him&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;the Boaty McBoatface name is still being used (to a point)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;So what is the big lesson about co-creation here? Essentially, co-creation is about trying to create a platform in which shared value can be derived. What co-creation isn’t is abdicating responsibility to the crowd, and then being surprised when they don’t respond as you had hoped.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We can learn more here from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dice_Man&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Dice Man&lt;/a&gt;, a novel based on a psychiatrist who made life decisions on the cast of a die.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;You must commit yourself to following the die, don’t put something on the list that you know you wouldn’t do even if the die choses it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;when-using-co-creation-to-develop-a-brand-dont-give-people-the-option-to-do-something-that-youre-not-prepared-to-do&quot;&gt;When using co-creation to develop a brand, don’t give people the option to do something that you’re not prepared to do.&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Bailey</name></author><summary type="html">Earlier this year the Natural Environment Research Council launched a poll to name their Royal Research Ship, using the hashtag #NameOurShip. A Royal Research Ship (RRS) conducts scientific research for Her Majesty’s Government no less, so this is respectable, important stuff.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accepting Impermanence in Brand Development</title><link href="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2014/10/17/accepting-impermanence-in-brand-development/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accepting Impermanence in Brand Development"/><published>2014-10-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-10-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2014/10/17/accepting-impermanence-in-brand-development</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://h3-dev-web6.halosvr.co.uk//2014/10/17/accepting-impermanence-in-brand-development/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;brands-are-works-in-progress-that-we-mistakenly-think-are-finished&quot;&gt;Brands are works in progress that we mistakenly think are finished.&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Instead, we should consider brands through the principles of wabi-sabi – a Japanese aesthetic ideology centred around the acceptance of persistent transience.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What I refer to here as ‘brand’ are not the spacial elements, such as the logo, website, product, etc, but the less tangible, such as the values, purpose, behaviours and experiences. In defining it as such, we can consider brands temporally rather than spatially.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A brand is not created exclusively by any one specific group of people – it is born (e.g. when a business/product is launched), it grows and develops (e.g. throughout the business/product lifespan), and it dies (e.g. when the business/product ends and people eventually forget about it). During its lifespan a brand will mean a myriad of things to any number of people.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In our networked, digital economy the content and value of brands are increasingly being created, or more accurately co-created, by all stakeholders (company, staff, users, etc). Digital technology has encouraged conversations between a company and its users and, importantly, between users themselves and has contributed to an emerging democratization. A good example are GoPro camera user videos as a prominent source of developing the GoPro brand and promoting the product. Brands are not only economic but are also social and cultural, and so are always open to development from stakeholders. Societal, cultural and economic environments are also constantly changing and developing, and therefore so too should brands.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If a brand is considered temporally, and is perpetually developing from the informed input of all stakeholders, what does this mean for businesses and the branding industry? A brand is not a static entity that you can create and then lock away in a brand guidelines document or a marketing plan. With a brand in perpetual development it is important to constantly realise where your brand is, and vitally how you might affect it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Throughout its lifespan a brand will inevitably have numerous visual guises, be that changing logos, identity systems etc as well as varying tactics with which to appeal to people. However, what these elements do is reflect and affect where a brand is at any point in time, helping to develop the brand in and for its current social, cultural and economic environment. Much like a business constantly develops its offering and working methods, so too in order to remain relevant (or popular) the brand must be in perpetual development and evolution while still communicating itself at key points in time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In some recent research psychologist Dan Gilbert has explained a phenomenon he calls the “End of history illusion,” where people imagine that the person they are now is the person they will be for the rest of time. He says, “Human beings are works in progress that mistakenly think they’re finished.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I suggest that the same is true for brands – brands are works in progress that we mistakenly think are finished. What branding industry professionals do is share the brand with the world, contextualise the brand, promote the brand, represent the brand – essentially help to shape and direct the brand in and for its current social, cultural and economic environment. What they or businesses don’t do is either fully control or own the brand.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Brands should never be considered finished. They aren’t static, but are temporal and evolutionary. They can be better understood if considered in a state of perpetual development. When considering brands we should accept the simple realities of wabi-sabi; nothing lasts, nothing is finished and nothing is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Bailey</name></author><summary type="html">Brands are works in progress that we mistakenly think are finished.</summary></entry></feed>